<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Mayor An act of Common Councell, prohibiting all strangers borne, and forrainers, to vse any trades, or keepe any maner of shops in any sort within this citty, liberties and freedome thereof.</title>
            <title>Acts &amp; Orders. 1606-04-15</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838673</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 844:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Mayor An act of Common Councell, prohibiting all strangers borne, and forrainers, to vse any trades, or keepe any maner of shops in any sort within this citty, liberties and freedome thereof.</title>
                  <title>Acts &amp; Orders. 1606-04-15</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Windet, printer to the honourable Cittie of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alien labor --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_the_London_Common_Council">
            <pb facs="tcp:3060:1"/>
            <head>By the Mayor. An Act of Common Councell, prohibiting all Strangers borne, and Forrainers, to vſe any trades, or keepe any maner of ſhops in any ſort within this Citty, Liberties and Freedome thereof.</head>
            <head type="sub">At a common Councel holden at the Guild-hall of this Citty, on the xv. day of April, In the fourth yeare of the Raign of our Soueraigne Lord IAMES, by the grace of God, King of England, France and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. and in the xxxix. yeare of his Raign of Scotland. It is ordained, &amp; eſtabliſhed as followeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here by the auncient Charters, Cuſtomes, Franchiſes, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Citty of London, confirmed by ſundrie Actes of Parliament, no perſon not being free of the ſaid Citty, may or ought to ſell, or put to ſale any wares or marchandiſes within the ſaid Cittie or the Liberties of the ſame by retaile, or keepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny open or inward ſhop, or other inward place or room for ſhew ſale, or putting to ſale, of any wares or marchandiſes, or for vſe of any Arte, Trade, Occupation, myſterie or handicraft with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame. And whereas alſo <hi>Edward</hi> ſometime King of England of famous memorie, the third of that name, by his Charter made and granted to the ſaide Citty in the fifteenth yeare of his Raigne, confirmed alſo by Parliament amongſt other things granted, that if any Cuſtomes in the ſaid Citty before that time obtayned and vſed, were in any part hard or defectiue, or any things in the ſame newlie ariſing, where remedie before that time was not ordained, ſhould need amendment, the Maior and Aldermen of the ſaid Citty and their Succeſſors, with the aſſent of the Communalty of the ſame Citty, might put and ordaine thereunto fit remedie, as often as it ſhould ſeeme expedient vnto them. So that ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſhould be profitable to the King for the profite of Cittizens and other his people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing to the ſaid Citty, and agreeable to reaſon. And wheras by force of the ſaid Cuſtoms, Franchiſes, and Liberties, and of the Charter laſt afore mentioned, confirmed as is afore ſpecified by Parliament, the Lord Maior, Aldermen and Commons of the ſaid Cittie, did the twelfth day of October in the third year of the raign of <hi>Edward</hi> ſomtime King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the fourth, as a thing thought fit and conuenient for that time, (amongſt other things) agree and ordaine, that the Basketmakers, Gold-wyerdrawers, and other forraines, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the libertie of the ſaid Cittie, holding open ſhoppes, in diuers places of the Cittie, and vſing myſteries within the ſaid Citie, ſhould not from thenceforth hold ſhoppes within the libertie of the Cittie aforeſaide. But if they would hold any ſhoppe, or dwell in the ſame Cittie, they ſhould dwell at Blanchapleton, and there holde ſhoppes, ſo as they might haue ſufficient dwelling there. And where alſo the Lord Maior, Aldermen and Commons of the ſaid Cittie, did afterwardes the ſixeteenth day of May, in the ſeuenteenth
<pb facs="tcp:3060:2"/>yeare of the Raigne of our late Soueraign Lord of famous memory King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, as a courſe thought fit and agreeable for that time, ordaine, eſtabliſh, and enact, that no manner of perſon or perſons being eſtrange from the Liberties of the ſaide Cittie, from thenceforth ſhould holde or keepe any open ſhoppe or ſhoppes within the ſaide Cittie or liberties of the ſame, neither with any Latteſſes before, nor yet without Latteſſe, certain numbers of the poore men occupying the feate of Botchers, Taylors and Coblers, onelie except, vpon paine of impriſonment, and alſo to forfeite and to pay xl. s. to the vſe of the Communaltie of this Citty, as oftentimes as he or they ſhould doe the contrarie. And where alſo the Lord Maior, Aldermen and Commons of the ſame Citty, did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the xx. day of Ianuary, in the ſaid xvij. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, (reciting that where at a common Councell holden the xvj. day of May, in the ſeauenteenth yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. It was ordained and enacted, that no manner of perſon or perſons being eſtrange from the Liberties of this Citty, from thenceforth ſhould holde or keepe any open ſhoppe or ſhoppes within this Citty or Liberties of the ſame, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with any Latteſſes before, nor yet without any Latteſſe vpon pain of impriſonment) Further, ordaine, and eſtabliſh, that if any perſon or perſons being forraine, ſhould holde and keepe open any ſhoppe or ſhoppes as is aforeſaid, he ſhould forfeite for euery time ſo doing xl. s. to be leuied by diſtreſſe, to the vſe of the Communaltie of the ſaide Cittie, by the Chamberlaine for the time being, or other Officer of this City, and alſo haue impriſonment by the diſcretion of the Maior and Aldermen for the time being.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as diuers and ſundry ſtrangers borne, and likewiſe Forreiners from the liberties of the ſaide Cittie, nothing regarding the ſaid auncient Charters, Franchiſes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, or liberties of the ſaide Cittie, and actes and ordinances heretofore made according to the ſame, but wholie intending their priuate profit, haue of late yeares deuiſed and practized by all ſiniſter and ſubtil meanes, how to defraud and defeat the ſaid Charters, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Cuſtoms, good orders, and ordinances, and to that end, do now inwardlie in priuie and ſecret places, vſually and ordinarily, ſhew, ſel, &amp; put to ſale, their Wares, &amp; Marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, and vſe Arts, Trades, Occupations, Miſteries, and Handicraftes within the ſaid Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Liberties of the ſame, to the great detriment and hurt of the Freemen of the ſaid Cittie, who pay Lot and Scot, beare Offices, and vndergoe other Charges which Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and others not Free are not chargeable withall nor will performe. For reformation of which diſorders, and for auoiding of ſuch preiudice and damage, as thereby groweth to the Freemen of the ſaid Cittie, and is more now of late vſed then was in any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſuffered, and to prouide for the common profite and good of the Freemen and Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of this Citty. It is therefore by the Lord Maior and Aldermen and Commons in this common Councell aſſembled, ordained and eſtabliſhed: That no perſon whatſoeuer not being free of the Cittie of London, ſhal at any time after the feaſt of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> now next enſuing, by any colour, way or meane whatſoeuer, either directly or indirectly by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or by any other, ſhew, ſel or put to ſale any wares, or marchandiſes whatſoeuer by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile within the Citty of London, or the Liberties or Suburbes of the ſame, vpon paine to
<pb facs="tcp:3060:3"/>forfeit to the Chamberlaine of the Citie, for the time being, to the vſe of the Maior and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie &amp; Citizens of the ſaid City the ſumme of fiue pounds of lawfull money of England, for euery time, wherein ſuch perſon ſhall ſhew, ſell or put to ſale any wares or marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes by retaile, within the ſaid Cittie, Liberties or Suburbes thereof, contrarie to the true intent and meaning hereof. And it is further ordained and eſtabliſhed, That no perſon whatſoeuer, not being free of this Citty, ſhall at any time after the ſaid Feaſt of Saint <hi>Michael,</hi> by any colour, way or meane whatſoeuer, directly or indirectly, by himſelfe, or by any other, keepe any ſhoppe, or other place whatſoeuer, inward or outward, for ſhew ſale, or putting to ſale of any wares, or marchandiſes whatſoeuer, by way of retaile, or vſe any Arte, Trade, Occupation, Myſtery or Handicraft whatſoeuer within the ſaide Citty, or the Liberties or Suburbes of the ſame, vpon paine to forfeite the ſumme of fiue poundes of lawfull money of England for euery time, wherein ſuch perſon ſhall keepe any ſhoppe or other place whatſoeuer, inward or outward, for ſhew, ſale, or putting to ſale of any wares or marchandizes whatſoeuer, by way of retaile, or vſe any Art, Trade, Occupation, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery or Handicraft whatſoeuer, within the ſaid Citty or Liberties or Suburbes of the ſame contrary to the true entent and meaning hereof. All which paines, penalties, forfeytures and ſummes of money to bee forfeyted by vertue of this Act, or ordinance, ſhall be recouered by action of debt, bill or plaint to be comenſed and proſequuted in the name of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine of the Citty of London for the time being, in the Kings Maieſties Court, to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Chamber of the Guild-hall of this Citty, before the Lord Maior and Aldermen of the ſame Citty, wherein no eſſoigne or wager of law ſhall be admitted or allowed for the Defendant. And that the Chamberlaine of the ſaid Cittie for the time being, ſhall in all ſutes to be proſequuted by virtue of this Act or Ordinaunce againſt any Offender, recouer the ordinarie Coſts of ſute to be expended in and about the proſequution thereof. And further that one equall third part of all forfeytures to be recouered by vertue hereof (the coſtes of ſuite for recouery of the ſame, being deducted and allowed) ſhall be after the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery and receipt thereof paide and deliuered to the Treaſurer of Chriſtes Hoſpitall, to be imployed towardes the reliefe of the poore children to be brought vp and maintained in the ſaid Hoſpitall, and one other equall third part to him, or them which ſhall firſt giue infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the offences, for which ſuch forfeitures ſhall growe and proſequute ſute in the name of the Chamberlaine of the ſaide Cittie for the recouery of the ſame, any thing in this Act to the Contrary notwithſtanding. Prouided alwayes, that this Act or ordinance, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing therein contained, ſhall not extend to any perſon or perſons, for bringing, or cauſing to be brought any victuals to be ſolde within this Citty and the Liberties thereof, but that they and euery of them may ſell victuals within the ſaid Citty, and the Liberties thereof, as they lawfully might haue done before the making hereof, any thing herein to the contrarie thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>John Windet,</hi> Printer to the Honourable Cittie of London, 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
